I remember the magic spell
From back when a rainbow stretched across the sky
In an instant, every corner of the world
Took on a brilliant hue
The voice of my heart
Always illuminates the path I need to take
It is because I doubt everything
That I know it to be true
Why does my heart still beat?
Why do my lungs still breathe?
Why is my chest burning with passion?
There's a reason for all of that
And, like the starry sky hidden behind the clouds
Like the ticket to a destination I lost somewhere
Like the history of the world from before I was born
You hold the answer just beyond my reach
If nothing else, I know that all too well
If nobody else, I know that all too well
Agreement
（幸田(こうだ)柾近(まさちか)）はぁ〜
I lost.
負けました
（桐山(きりやま) 零(れい)）
その人は父の友人だった
He was my dad's best friend.
う〜ん　どうして
竜を取らなかったの？
Why didn't you capture the dragon?
（幼い零）あ… 竜を取っていると
詰まされそうな気がしたから
I had a feeling if I captured the dragon, you would've checkmated me.
それに—
And it looked like I could checkmate you at first glance.
一目 詰みそうに見えたから
竜に飛びつくと思ったのになぁ
And here I thought you would go for the dragon.
You don't play like a child.
子供らしくないなぁ 君
詰ましに きやがった
You came to checkmate me.
（零）父の友達なのに
その人が来ると—
Even though he was my dad's friend,
every time he came over, I would get happy and restless.
僕は なぜか
そわそわ うれしくなった
（零の父）
幸田 遅くなってすまん
急患が入っちまって
Kouda, sorry I'm late.
An emergency came up.
Oh, that must've been a pain.
（幸田）ああ お疲れ
Sorry to keep you waiting.
（零の父）
待たせちまって 悪かったな
No, that's fine.
（幸田）いやあ 大丈夫
零君が相手してくれてたから
I was playing with Rei.
Oh? So how'd it go?
（零の父）
へえ　で どうだった？
（幸田）
ハハッ 負けちゃったよ
I lost.
そうか
I see.
Apparently, he and my dad used to be in the federation together.
（零）父とその人は ずっと前
奨励会で一緒だったらしい
Rei made an interesting move just now.
零君 さっき
面白い手を指してきたよ
昔のお前と
指してるみたいな気になった
It reminded me of the kind of moves you used to make.
It looks like he's been studying quite a bit.
かなり 勉強してるみたいだな
Right?
（零）将棋は苦手だったけれど
Shogi wasn't my favorite thing, but it was precious time that I could spend with my busy father.
忙しい父と一緒に過ごせる
大事な時間だから
So I tried my hardest.
一生懸命 頑張ってた
I wish he'd play outside a little more...
俺としては もうちょっと
外で遊んでほしいんだけど
そういう所も似ちゃったかな 俺に
but I guess the apple doesn't fall far from the tree.
（零）僕は近所でも学校でも
いじめられっ子で
In the neighborhood and at school, I got bullied a lot.
I just couldn't seem to make any friends.
どうしても友達が作れなかった
The kids in my class would have bewildering conversations,
クラスの子たちの話す言葉は
目まぐるしくって
何を話してるのか追いつけなくて
異国の言葉のように聞こえた
and I couldn't keep up with them.
It was like they were speaking a foreign language.
And yet, the words he said while on the other side of the shogi board
なのに 盤を挟んでの
その人の言葉は—
always made a deep impression on me.
ちゃんといつも
僕の中に しみてきた
Even though he's an adult, he really talked to me.
（零）大人なのに ちゃんと僕に
語りかけてくれてるって
それが分かった
I understood that.
そんな人 家族以外では
ただ一人だった
He was the only person outside of my family who did that.
Modern Shogi
Huh?
（零）え？
モモちゃんを保育園に迎えに？
Pick Momo up from kindergarten?
（川本(かわもと)あかり）
そうなの　伯母がね
Yes. You see, my aunt...
You've met her before, right?
そう 会ったことあるでしょ？
She's the owner of the club I work at.
うちの店 「美咲」のママ
She made a misstep while going
down some stairs and hurt her foot.
階段 踏み外して
足 打撲しちゃって—
I'm at the hospital now.
今 病院なの
（美咲(みさき)）はぁー
ヒナは 部活で 連絡取れなくて
おじいちゃんは お店だし
Hina isn't picking up because she's with her club,
and Grandpa is busy at the shop.
ごめんね
頼まれてくれる？
Sorry, but could you do me this favor?
（保育士）
モモちゃーん お迎えよ
Momo, time to go home!
Okay!
（川本(かわもと)モモ）はーい
あーっ！ 零ちゃんだ
It's Rei!
Hello.
どうも
（零）楽しそうだな
It seems she's having fun.
モモちゃん それ 何の歌だい？
Momo, what song is that?
Um, it's the cat song!
うーんとねー「ねこのうた」
知ってる？ フフフ…
Do you know it?
ううん 初めて聞くな
Nope.
This is the first time I've heard it.
Hey!
My hat's running away!
（モモ）モモの お帽子がー！
（零）あっ！ あー よかった
Thank goodness.
A little longer and it would've fallen into the river.
もうちょっとで
川に落ちるとこだった
ワン ワォーン！
（モモ）キャーッ！
（犬）
わぁー！ かわいい女の子だ
あーそびーましょー！
A cute little girl! Let's play!
（女性）駄目よ シロ！
（モモ）ワァーン
Stop it, Casper!
I like her! I like her!
（犬）ハフハフ 好き好き！
（モモ）わぁー！
Momo!
モモちゃん！ モモちゃん！
（犬）
キャー！ ハフハフ！
ねえねえねえ 小さい人 遊ぼう！
C'mon, little one! Let's play!
ねえねえねえ 遊ぼうよ
ハフハフ ハフ！
C'mon, c'mon! Let's play!
Slam
. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . .
Huff
Paw
Wag
Huff
Paw
Wag
Huff
Paw
Wag
Huff
Paw
わぁーん！
（零）モモちゃん 大丈夫？
Momo, are you okay?
Did you hit your forehead?
おでこは？ ぶつけてない？
（女性）
すいません！ すいません！
I'm sorry! I'm sorry!
（犬）
あ… 泣かせてしまいました
Oh no, I made her cry.
Sadness...
I'm sorry.
ごめんなさい
Sadness...
（零）ほら 着いたよ
モモちゃん
Look, we're home, Momo.
Let's tend to those scratches.
（零）手当てしないとね
（モモ）ううっ… うっ…
（零）っしょ…
モモちゃん
お薬箱 どこか分かる？
Momo, do you know where the first-aid kit is?
（モモ）ヒッ…うっ… うん
Yeah.
よく見せて
Let me see.
あぁ…
傷口に砂が入っちゃってるな
Oh, sand got into the scratches.
Here, rinse your hand off.
（零）はい おてて
ジャーっとして
Rei, it hurts.
（モモ）零ちゃん 痛い
（零）
ごめんね ちょっと我慢して
Sorry. Hang in there a little longer, okay?
Um, first...
（零）
あ… えーっと まず… 消毒
Disinfectant.
That and gauze...
それと ガーゼと
Brother!
（ちひろ）お兄ちゃん
（モモ）零ちゃん？
Rei?
（零）今日は 本当に
すいませんでした
I'm really sorry about today.
Rei, children often fall down,
so you don't have to worry about it.
（あかり）零君… ああもう…
子供が転ぶなんて
しょっちゅうある事なんだから
そんなに気にしないで
It doesn't hurt anymore!
モモ もう痛くないよ
（クロちゃん）うーん まぶしい
So bright...
Um, I'm thirsty, so can I get some milk meowbe?
（シロちゃん）
あのー 喉が渇いたので—
牛乳か何か いただけまてんか？
Rei really felt bad about that, huh?
（川本(かわもと)ひなた）
零ちゃん すっごく気にしてたね
He hardly ate anything at dinner.
ご飯も ちょっとしか
食べなかったし
モモ いっぱい泣いて
困らせたんでしょう？
You probably cried too much and made him worry, Momo.
モモ 泣かなかったもん
I didn't cry at all!
（ミケちゃん）まだ 晩ごはん
もらってないですニャー
I haven't had dinner yet!
Gigantic liars
But Rei was crying.
でもね 零ちゃんは 泣いてた
涙が ぽーろ ぽーろ してた
モモ 見たもん
Big tears drip-dropped down his cheeks.
I saw it!
（ひなた）えーっ？ 何で？
Why?
Why was he crying?
何で零君が泣くの？
（あかり）
ああ それはね きっと…
I'm sure it's because...
思い出しちゃったんだね
he remembered something sad.
（あかり）零ちゃんにもね—
Rei had...
妹がいたんだよ
a little sister too.
One day, my normal life suddenly ended, as if it had been ripped away from me.
（零）僕の日常は—
ある日 いきなり
引きちぎられるように—
唐突に終わった
When I returned from the school trip,
my precious father, mother, and little sister...
遠足から戻ると
僕の大切な
父と母と小さな妹は
had become cold, stiff, and spotted masses of flesh.
冷たくて固い
まだらの塊になっていた
（親戚Ａ）飲酒運転の
トラックの巻き添えですって
They said it was an incident with a drunken truck driver.
（親戚Ｂ）
三人とも即死だったらしいな
Apparently, the three of them were killed instantly.
I wonder what will happen to their son.
（親戚Ｃ）
息子さんはどうなるのかしら
His father's younger sister, Kiwako, will probably take him in, right?
（親戚Ｄ）妹の貴和子さんが
引き取るんじゃないの？
（親戚Ｅ）まさか—
There's no way that woman would agree to it.
あの女が そんな役
買って出るわけないだろう
And his grandfather is far too old...
（親戚Ｆ）
おじいさまも もうお年だしね
（零の祖父）このばか者！
You fool!
What's going to happen to the hospital?!
病院はどうするつもりだ！
You finally gave up shogi and
agreed to take over after I retired.
せっかく お前が 将棋をやめて
継いでくれて
I thought everything would turn out well...
これからは
全部うまくいくと…
（貴和子の夫）
お義父さん 大丈夫ですよ
Father-in-law, it'll be okay.
You've got me. I'll take care of everything.
僕がいますよ
僕に任せてください
（貴和子）そうよ 最初から
そう言ってたのに—
Yes, that's what I've been saying from the beginning.
But you only thought about my brother.
父さんは 兄さんばっかり
Poor child.
かわいそうに
I'll find a good orphanage for Rei.
零君には ちゃんと私が
いい施設を探しますからね
I didn't know what an orphanage was.
（零）施設という所が
どんな場所かは分からなかった
でも 今までは 学校で
どんなにつらくても
But...
until then, no matter how tough school was,
in the evening I could return to my
warm room and relax safely by myself.
夕方には
あたたかい自分の部屋で
一人になって
ほっと落ち着くことができた
But if I went to an orphanage, even if I went back to my room, somebody would always be there.
でも そこに入ったら
帰っても 誰かが ずっといて
眠るときも 誰かがいて
Somebody would even be there when I went to sleep.
もう ほっとできる時間は—
I realized that out of the 365 days in a year,
I wouldn't have a single moment to feel relief.
365日の中で 一瞬も無くなるのだ
ということだけは分かった
そして その人は やって来た
And then he arrived.
Many of my blood relatives had come to the funeral,
葬儀には 血のつながった親戚が
たくさん集まっていたけれど
その時 部屋に入ってきた
その人だけが—
but out of everyone in the room, he was the only one...
who made me feel so nostalgic that I wanted to cry out.
叫び出したいほど 懐かしかった
Like I said, my husband will be taking over Kiriyama Hospital.
ですから 桐山医院は
主人が継ぎます
口出しは ご無用ですわ
There's nothing else to say.
I can't believe Kiwako's terrible attitude.
（親戚Ｇ）まったく
貴和子さんの態度ったら…
She's always been like that.
（親戚Ｈ）あの子は
昔から ああだったわ
Shhh, we're in front of the deceased.
（親戚Ｉ）
しっ！ お前 ご霊前だぞ
But...
だって…
Do you...
（幸田）君は 将棋 好きか？
like shogi?
This was when we formed our agreement.
（零）これが 契約の瞬間だった
将棋の神様と僕の
醜いうそで固めた…
The god of shogi and I were bound to each other by an ugly lie.
Yes.
（幼い零）はい
It was a lie.
（零）うそだった
That was the first time in my life that I lied in order to live.
人生で初めての
生きるための—
そして 決して戻れない…
I could never go back.
Then, the ropes were cut and the curtain dropped,
そうして 幕は どうしようもなく
切って落とされ—
and I became the child of a shogi family.
僕は 将棋の家の子になった
Agreement
One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest
It's coming undone.
ほつれてる
Pulling it will only make it worse.
あぁ 駄目だ
引っ張ったら余計…
こういうのって
どうしたらいいんだ？
What should I do in this case?
（零）あった これか？
Found it.
Is this it?
（零）将棋の家で
僕を待っていたのは—
Waiting for me at that house of shogi were the true children of the family,
同じく 棋士を目指す
その家の 本当の子供たち
who also aspired to be professional shogi players.
Don't be so full of yourself! You're just a "zero"!
（幸田(こうだ)香子(きょうこ)）
いい気になんないで！
ゼロのくせに
（零）四つ上の姉の香子と
同じ年で 弟の小３の歩(あゆむ)だった
Kyouko, who was four years older than me,
and Ayumu, a third-grader who was the same age.
（香子）フン
Dear, please forgive her. She's had enough.
（幸田の妻）お父さん どうか
もう この辺で許してやって
駄目だ
No.
Kyouko's just a girl!
（幸田の妻）
香子は 女の子なのよ
将棋うんぬん以前の問題だ
This isn't just about shogi.
How dare she strike an opponent after losing?!
負けて 相手を殴るなんて！
But...
（幸田の妻）でも…
Father was strict with Kyouko.
（零）父は 香子には厳しかった
I think he was harder on her because of her skill.
たぶん 彼女の強さが 余計に
父にそうさせたのだと思う
She was as tempestuous as a storm in every respect.
全ての面において
彼女は 嵐のように激しかった
棋風も 気性も その美しさも
Her shogi style, her disposition, and her beauty too.
Hey. What do you think you're staring at, twerp?
ちょっと
何じろじろ見てんのよ チビ
（幼い零）ウッ！
（幸田）コラッ！ 香子！
Knock it off, Kyouko!
Um, Dad...
（幼い零）あの… お父さん
（幸田）ん？
（幼い零）お代わりを
Would you like some more?
ああ 頼む
Yes, please.
Hey, what was that just now?
ちょっと 何？ 今の
What do you mean, "Dad"?
お父さんって 何それ
Um, I'm sorry.
はっ あの… ごめんなさい
Is it weird?
変か？ 私が
そう呼べって言ったんだよ
I told him to call me that.
Why? That boy is an apprentice, isn't he?
何で？
その子 内弟子でしょ
You didn't adopt him, so why would he call you "Dad"?
養子でもないのに
何でお父さんなのよ
うちの中で 師匠と
呼ばれるのも落ち着かん
I couldn't relax if he called me "Master" in the house.
Can't you think of me as being his "shogi father"?
将棋のお父さんだからじゃ
駄目なのか？
That reminds me, Inoue from the
training hall told me something, Rei.
あっ そういえば
道場の井上さんに聞いたぞ
零 お前 アマ名人の
橋本さんに勝ったんだってな
He said you beat Hashimoto, the amateur Master.
That's amazing!
すごいじゃないか
（零）父は将棋を愛していた
Father loved shogi.
良くも悪くも
全てが将棋中心だった
Good or bad, everything was centered around shogi for him.
だから 彼を愛する者は
強くなるしかなかった
Therefore, those who loved him
had no choice but to get better...
I had a question about losing entrance into the league...
彼の視界に入り続けるために
...in order to stay in his field of vision.
And then...
そして 最初におかしくなったのは
歩だった
Ayumu was the first one to have a breakdown.
Ayumu seems to be in low spirits at school lately.
（教師）歩君 最近
学校でもふさぎがちです
His grades are dropping too.
成績も落ちています
Has something happened at home?
ご家庭で 何か
あったのでしょうか？
Well, the apprentice we've taken in has surpassed him at shogi.
（幸田の妻）あの… 今
引き取ってる内弟子の子に—
将棋で抜かれてしまって
それで…
I'm quitting shogi.
（幸田(こうだ) 歩(あゆむ)）僕 もう 将棋やめる
（幼い零）ハァ ハァ
（幸田）無理だよ
It's impossible.
If he won't continue unless someone persuades him, it's pointless.
他人が説得しなけりゃ
続かないようなら 駄目なんだ
But—
（幼い零）でも…
If he isn't someone who can convince himself and make progress on his own, it's pointless.
（幸田）自分で自分を説得しながら
進んでいける人間でなければ—
駄目なんだ
プロになるのが
ゴールなんじゃない
Becoming a professional isn't the goal.
The path after is so long it'll make your head spin.
なってからの方が
気が遠くなるほど長いんだ
The further you go, the steeper it becomes,
and you'll be all alone.
進めば進むほど 道は険しく
周りに 人はいなくなる
自分で自分を
メンテナンスできる人間しか—
Only someone who can keep themselves together will continue to make progress.
どのみち 先へは
進めなくなるんだよ
（香子）何で？
Why?!
Why do I have to quit the federation?!
何で 私が 奨励会を
やめなきゃなんないの？
If you can't beat Rei, there's no point in continuing.
（幸田）零に勝てないのなら
これ以上は無理だ
If you make it to 1-dan,
there'll be better players everywhere.
初段まで行けば これ以上が
ゴロゴロいるんだぞ
（幸田）分かってるだろう 香子
You understand, right, Kyouko?
（将棋関係者Ａ）結局 残ったのは
他人の子供だけか
So in the end, only someone else's kid made the cut?
That's Kiriyama's son, right?
（将棋関係者Ｂ）
あの子 桐山の子だろう？
So he went out of his way to raise his rival's child,
who then upstaged his own kids.
ライバルの子を
わざわざ育てて—
自分の子が
食われちまったってわけか
How ironic.
（将棋関係者Ａ）皮肉なもんだな
（零）その後 香子は
街で遊びまわるようになり
After that, Kyouko spent a lot of time gallivanting around town,
while Ayumu shut himself in his room and became immersed in video games.
歩は 部屋に籠もって
ゲームに のみ込まれ
The three of us no longer spent time together.
三人で過ごすことは なくなった
I couldn't bear the situation,
so I became increasingly engrossed in shogi.
居たたまれない僕は ますます
将棋の勉強にのめり込み
そして
And then,
by the end of my second year of junior high, and one step away from turning pro,
僕は 中二の終わりに
プロの一歩手前—
I had reached the 3-dan league.
三段リーグにまで 到達した
There is a species of bird that does not raise its
own children, but engages in "brood parasitism."
（テレビの音声）
鳥には 自分で子育てをせず
たく卵をする種があります
カッコウは モズやホオジロの巣に
卵を産み付け—
The cuckoo lays its eggs in the nests of shrikes or meadow buntings.
かえったひなは
もともとの子供たちを—
The hatched chick then tosses the original
eggs out of the nest before they're hatched.
卵のうちに全て外へ落とし
巣を占領します
In this way, it takes over the nest.
何も知らない育ての親は—
When the parents return, none the wiser,
they work hard to feed and raise the chicks of the bird that murdered their own offspring.
自分の子を殺した他人の子に
せっせと餌を運び 育て続けます
（零）ああ 僕だ
Oh, that's me.
Even if the cuckoo chick outgrows its surrogate parents,
（テレビの音声）
たとえ カッコウのひなが—
自分より
大きくなってしまっても—
they will continue to feed their chick.
いつまでも 餌を運び続けるのです
That bird is me.
（零）この鳥は僕だ
You're really not going to high school?
（零の担任）本当に 高校には
行かないのかね？
Yes.
（零）はい
Are you sure that's what you want?
（零の担任）
本当にそれでいいのかい？
（零）学校というのは—
I think school is a place you go to in order to choose the course of your future.
将来の道を 選ぶために
通う所だと思います
だから もう 僕には
必要ありません
So I don't think it's necessary for me any longer.
このまま行けば 今年中…
今年は無理でも—
If I continue at this rate, this year—
or if that proves impossible, next year,
I'll move up from the 3-dan league and turn pro.
来年には 三段リーグを抜け
僕は プロになります
将棋に集中したいんです
I want to focus on shogi.
After I turn pro, I'll do my best to improve my performance...
プロになって 頑張って
少しでも成績を上げて
（零）家を出よう
I'll leave that house.
...win tournaments and money, and save that money...
勝ち星をつかんで
お金を稼いで
I have to leave there as soon as possible.
（零）一刻も早く出なければ
...so I can become independent.
そして自立したいんです
僕があの家の人たちを…
父さんを食い尽くす前に
Before I devour the members of that family.
Before I devour Dad.
I did it.
（零）出来た
It's a little zig-zaggy...
ちょっとギザギザに
なっちゃったけど
but it'll be okay.
大丈夫
これでもう これ以上 ほつれない
It won't come undone anymore.
Good.
よかった
まだ着ていられる
I can still wear it.
（幸田）何だ 零　寒いのか？
What is it, Rei? Are you cold?
I'm the cuckoo...
（零）僕は カッコウだ
そうだ とりあえず
これを着てなさい
I know.
For now, put this on.
私ので悪いが
I hope it's okay that it's mine.
...standing over the lives that were thrust aside.
（零）押しのけた命の上に立ち
（幸田）ハッハッハ
ちょっと でかすぎるな
It's a little big on you.
Th-That's okay.
だ… 大丈夫です
うれしいです
I'm happy to wear it.
It's really warm.
すごくあったかいです
（零）春をうたえと呼ぶ声を聞く
I hear them calling out a song of spring.
Thank you, Dad.
ありがとう お父さん
And I think, that if I truly were a bird, then at least...
そして思う
いっそ本当に鳥だったらと
そうしたら
I would never have known this relentless pain.
こんな激しい痛み
知らずに済んだのにと
One Flew Over the Cuckoo's Nest
Like a resplendent meteor shower
Your words enter my ears and catch fire
They come together like a school of fish
And form a warm corner in my once chilly bosom
As I stood in place, not knowing the right way to reach out
Your hand reached out to touch mine
And no matter how many nights may pass
That warmth still lingers and pulses within
Your very presence shines a bright light on every part of my life
Your racing heartbeat resonates with my frozen heart and sets it ablaze
Before long, the fire dies out
Leaving just one smoldering ember
Which remains with me and won't ever go away
Living inside of me in a place closest to my heart
Next Episode Preview
I want to go somewhere.
Episode 6
（零）
どこか行きたい
Chinatown in Yokohama!
（ひなた）
中華街！ 横浜の
With meat dumplings,
or shrimp in chili sauce.
肉まんとか
エビチリとか
How about a place with a beautiful beach,
where I can relax?
（あかり）
海がきれいで—
のんびりできる所かな
（モモ）芋ほり！
I wanna dig for potatoes!
And then, a soy sauce factory!
あとね おしょうゆ工場
Can we be a bit more subtle?
（零）
包みましょうよ—
Maybe a little more tactful,
and not so straightforward.
もっと こう
オブラートに
ストレートすぎますよ
Illustration: Higuchi Yuuko
（モモ）３…
"March... March comes in like a lion."
３月のライオン
モモは
ライオンさんより
I like Bodoro more than lions!
ボドロが好きです